《功夫熊猫》
Legend tells of a legendary warrior...
传奇故事传颂着一名传奇大侠
...whose kung fu skills were the stuff of legend.
他的功夫出神入化
He traveled the land in search of worthy foes.
他走遍天涯 独孤求败
I see you like to chew. Maybe you should chew on my fist!
你挺喜欢吃啊 有种吃我一拳
The warrior said nothing for his mouth was full.
大侠一言不发 因为吃了个满嘴
Then he swallowed. And then he spoke.
他一口吞下 这才开口道
Enough talk. Let's fight!
"少废话 接招吧!"
Shashabooey!
拿命来!
He was so deadly in fact,
他的一招一式如此彪悍
that his enemies would go blind from overexposure to pure awesomeness.
他的敌人目不暇接 瞠目结舌
- My eyes! - He's too awesome!
- 我的眼睛啊! - 他太彪悍啦!
- And attractive. - How can we repay you?
- 太迷人了! - 我们何以回报?
There is no charge for awesomeness.
彪悍不求回报
Or attractiveness.
迷人更无所需
Kablooey!
出事了!
It mattered not how many foes he faced.
他征战无数
They were no match for his bodacity!
无人匹敌
Never before had a panda been so feared! And so loved.
从没有哪只熊猫能让人如此畏惧 又让人如此爱戴
Even the most heroic heroes in China,
即使是神州大地之上最英勇的勇士们
the Furious Five,
"盖世五侠"
bowed in respect to this great master.
也心怀敬意地拜倒在这位大师脚下
We should hang out.
一块儿出去玩玩?
Agreed.
同意
But hanging out would have to wait.
但出去玩的事情得先放一边
Because when you're facing the 10,000 demons of Demon Mountain,
因为当你眼前是恶魔山的万千暴徒时
there's only one thing that matters and that's...
正经事只有一件 那就是...
Po! Get up!
阿宝 快起床!
You'll be later for work!
要误生意了
What?
啥?
Po! Get up!
阿宝 快起床!
Po. What are you doing up there?
阿宝 你磨蹭啥呢?
Nothing.
没啥
Monkey! Mantis! Orane! Viper! Tigress!
金猴、螳螂、仙鹤、灵蛇、娇虎
Po! Let's go! You're late for work.
阿宝 快点 都误生意了
Coming!
来啦...
Sorry, Dad.
对不起 老爸
Sorry doesn't make the noodles.
对不起可变不出面条来
What were you doing up there? All that noise.
你在楼上搞什么名堂 稀里哗啦的
Nothing. I just had a crazy dream.
没什么 就是个乱七八糟的梦
About what?
什么梦?
What were you dreaming about?
梦到什么了?
What was I...?
梦到了...我梦见了...
I was dreaming about...
我梦见了...
...noodles.
面条
Noodles? You were really dreaming about noodles?
面条? 你真梦见面条了?
Yeah. What else would I be dreaming about?
没错 不然还能梦见啥?
Careful! That soup is sharp.
小心 汤很锋利哦（有飞镖）
Oh, happy day!
噢 太让人高兴了!
My son, finally having the noodle dream!
我儿子终于做了个面条梦了!
You don't know how long I've been waiting for this moment.
噢 你不知道 我等这一刻都等了多久
This is a sign, Po.
这是个好兆头 阿宝
A sign of what?
什么好兆头
You are almost ready to be entrusted with the secret ingredient
我终于可以把我的秘之又秘
of my Secret Ingredient Soup.
私酿密汤的配方传给你了
Then you will fulfill your destiny and take over the restaurant!
这样你就能不辱使命 继承这间饭馆了
As I took it over from my father who took it over from his father...
就像我子承父业 父承爷业一样
...who won it from a friend in mahjong.
这店可是爷爷打麻将从朋友手里赢来的
Dad, Dad, Dad, it was just a dream.
老爸 老爸 这不过是场梦
No, it was the dream.
不 这是启示之梦
We are noodle folk. Broth runs through our veins.
我们可是面条世家 连血管里都流着面汤
But, Dad, didn't you ever want to do something else?
可是 老爸 你有没有...想过做点别的
Something besides noodles?
除了面条之外的
Actually, when I was young and crazy,
其实 我年少轻狂的时候
I thought about running away and learning how to make tofu.
曾想过 离家出走 学做豆腐
Why didn't you?
那你干吗不做?
Because it was a stupid dream.
因为这是个黄梁蠢梦
Can you imagine me making tofu?
你能想象我做豆腐的样子吗?
Tofu.
豆腐?
No! We all have our place in this world.
别提了! 我们各有其命
Mine is here, and yours is...
我的命就是在这儿煮面 而你…
I know, is here.
我知道 也是在这儿
No, it's at tables 2, 5, 7, and 12.
错! 是送2号桌 5号桌 7号桌 还有12号桌
Service with a smile.
别忘了微笑服务
Well done, students... if you were trying to disappoint me.
干得漂亮 徒弟们 要想不让我失望
Tigress, you need more ferocity! Monkey, greater speed.
娇虎 力道要更强 金猴 速度要更快
Orane, height. Viper, subtlety. Mantis...
仙鹤 凌空要更高 灵蛇 出招要更敏锐 螳螂...
- Master Shifu. - What?!
- 师父 - 插什么嘴
It's Master Oogway. He wants to see you.
乌龟大师 他想见您
Master Oogway, you summoned me? Is something wrong?
乌龟大师 您召见我 是出什么事了吗?
Why must something be wrong for me to want to see my old friend?
为何非要出事 才能与老友相聚呢?
So, nothing's wrong?
这么说 没出啥事?
Well, I didn't say that.
也不能说没事
You were saying?
您是想说...
I have had a vision.
我看见一些幻相
Tai Lung will return.
太郞会重现江湖
That is impossible! He is in prison.
这不可能 他还在牢里呢
Nothing is impossible.
一切皆有可能
Zeng!
小曾
Fly to Ohorh-Gom prison and tell them,
马上飞到桃岗天牢去告诉他们
to double the guards, double their weapons, double everything!
看守加倍 兵器加倍 统统都加倍
Tai Lung does not leave that prison!
绝不能让大龙逃出大牢
Yes, Master Shifu!
遵命! 师父大师
One often meets his destiny on the road he takes to avoid it.
古语有云 子欲避之 反促遇之
We must do something! We can't let him march on the valley and take his revenge!
我们不能无动于衷 我们不能让他闯入谷中泄愤
He'll...
他会...
Your mind is like this water my friend.
你心如此水 我的朋友
When it is agitated it becomes difficult to see.
乱则不明
But if you allow it to settle...
但若心如止水
...the answer becomes clear.
答案便尽现眼前
The Dragon Scroll.
神龙卷轴
It is time.
是时候了
But who? Who is worthy to be trusted with the secret to limitless power?
可传给谁? 谁值得信任 能把这无限的力量交付与他
To become the Dragon Warrior?
让他成为"神龙大侠"
I don't know.
我也不知道
Excuse me. Pardon me. Sorry.
借过 抱歉
Watch it!
嘿 看着点走 阿宝
Sorry. Suck it up!
对不起 收腹!
Sorry. A thousand pardons.
对不起 一千个抱歉
What?
什么?
Master Oogway's choosing the Dragon Warrior! Today!
乌龟大师要选神龙大侠! 就在今天!
Everyone! Get to the Jade Palace! One of the Five is gonna get the Dragon Scroll!
大伙们 快去翡翠宫 五侠之一要得到神龙卷轴了!
We've waited 1,000 years for this! Take the bowl!
千年等一回啊! 碗上端快去啊!
This is the greatest day in kung fu history! Just go!
这可是功夫史上最重要的一天 别操心付账了 快去吧!
Po! Where are you going?
阿宝 你要去哪儿?
To the Jade Palace.
去翡翠宫
You're forgetting your noodle cart.
可你忘了你的面条车了
The whole valley will be there and you'll sell noodles to all of them.
整个山谷的人都会去 你可以大卖特卖
Selling noodles?
卖面条?
But, Dad, I was thinking, maybe I...
可是 老爸 我在想我可不可以...
- Yeah? - I was thinking maybe I...
- 什么? - 我在想我可不可以...
...could also sell the bean buns. They're about to go bad.
可不可以也顺道卖点豆包 省的放坏了
That's my boy!
真是个好孩子
I told you that dream was a sign.
我说过那个梦是个好兆头
Yeah. Glad I had it.
是哈 真高兴我做了这个梦...
- I'm a kung fu warrior! - Me, too!
- 我是功夫大侠 - 我也是
- There's spots at the top. - Let's go.
- 山都连上天了 - 咱快点
Come on. Come on!
加把劲
Almost there.
就要到了
What?
什么
No! Oh, no!
不会吧 不 不
- Sorry, Po. - We'll bring you back a souvenir.
- 不好意思 阿宝 - 我们会给你带纪念品的
No. I'll bring me back a souvenir.
不 我要自己带纪念品下来
It is an historic day.
这是历史性的一天
Isn't it, Master Oogway?
是吧 乌龟大师?
Yes, and one I feared I would not live to see.
没错 我还怕我不能活着等到这天
Are your students ready?
你的徒弟们准备好了吗?
Yes, Master Oogway.
好了 乌龟大师
Know this, old friend.
老朋友 你得明白
Whomever I choose will not only bring peace to the valley...
不管我选了谁 不仅是给山谷带来平和
...but also to you.
也是给你
Let the tournament begin!
比武大会现在开始
Yeah.
耶!
No, no, wait!
不! 等等
I'm coming! Wait, wait!
我来了! 等等!
Yes!
先别关
Hey! Open the door!
嗨 把门开开!
Let me in!
让我进去!
Oitizens of the Valley of Peace
平和谷的居民们
it is my great honor to present to you... Tigress!
我深感荣幸 为你们介绍 娇虎
Viper! Orane! Monkey! Mantis!
灵蛇 仙鹤 金猴 螳螂
The Furious Five!
"盖世五侠"
Yeah, the Furious Five!
哇! 盖世五侠!
Warriors, prepare!
大侠们准备
Wait. No. Oh, peeky-hole.
等等 不 噢 门孔
- Ready for battle! - Yeah.
- 准备比武 - 耶
The Thousand Tongues of Fire.
数千火舌
Look at that.
哇噢 看看那个
Hey! Get out of the way!
嗨 别挡着我!
And finally Master Tigress!
最后出场的是 娇虎大师
And believe me, citizens you have not seen anything yet.
相信我 居民们 你们将大开眼界
I know!
我知道!
Master Tigress! Face Iron OX and his Blades of Death.
娇虎上场 为您表演 大战钢铁牛和他的绝命刀
I sense the Dragon Warrior is among us.
我感觉到"神龙大侠"就在我们中间
Oitizens of the Valley of Peace,
平和谷的居民们
Master Oogway will now choose the Dragon Warrior!
乌龟大师现在要选出"神龙大侠"了
Oh, no! No, no, wait!
什么? 不不 等等!
Yeah.
有了
Po!
阿宝
What are you doing?!
你在干什么?
What does it look like I'm doing?! Stop!
你说我在干什么? 别...别吹!
I'm going to see the Dragon Warrior!
我要去看"神龙大侠"!
But I don't understand. You finally had the noodle dream!
可我不懂 你才做了面条梦啊
I lied. I don't dream about noodles, Dad.
我骗你的 老爸 我没梦见面条
I love kung fu!
我爱功夫!
Come on, son. Let's get back to work.
算了吧 儿子 还是回家卖面吧
OK.
好吧
Come back!
回来!
What's going on?
什么情况
Where...?
这是哪儿
What are you pointing...?
你指什么
OK. Sorry.
哦 对不起
I just wanted to see who the Dragon Warrior was.
我只是想看看谁才是"神龙大侠"
How interesting.
真有意思啊
Master, are you pointing at me?
大师 您是指我吗?
- Him. - Who?
- 他 - 谁?
- You. - Me?
- 你 - 我?
The universe has brought us the Dragon Warrior!
上苍降"神龙大侠"给我们!
- What? - What?!
- 什么? - 什么?!
- What?! - What?!
- 什么?! - 什么?!
Stop, wait! Who told you to...?
停下! 等等! 谁叫你们去的!
Master Oogway, wait.
乌龟大师 等等
That flabby panda can't possibly be the answer to our problem.
那只又肥又胖的熊猫怎么可能是神龙大侠
You were about to point at Tigress and that thing fell in front of her!
你正要指娇虎的时候 那只破烂熊猫从天而降
That was just an accident!
这纯属意外!
There are no accidents.
世上无意外
Forgive us, Master. We have failed you.
请您原谅 师父 我们让您失望了
No. If the panda has not quit by morning,
不 要是明天那熊猫还没打退堂鼓
then I will have failed you.
那是我让你们失望了
Wait! Wait, wait, wait! I bring a message...
等一下! 我是来送信的
...from Master Shifu.
替师父大师而来
What?!
什么?!
"Double the guard?!"
守卫加倍
"Extra precautions?!"
警戒加倍
"Your prison may not be adequate?!"
你的天牢还不够严密
You doubt my prison security?!
你怀疑我天牢的安全?
Absolutely not.
绝对没有
Shifu does. I'm just the messenger.
师父这么说 我就是个传话的
I'll give you a message for your Master Shifu.
那么请你代我传个话给师父
Escape from Ohorh-Gom prison is impossible!
从桃岗天牢越狱 绝无可能!
Lmpressive, isn't it?
叹为观止吧?
It's very impressive.
是 是 叹为观止
相当的叹为观止
One way in, one way out.
进道出路 只有一条
One thousand guards and one prisoner.
千名守卫 只为一囚
Yes, except that prisoner...
没错 只是那个囚徒是...
...is Tai Lung.
大龙
Take us down.
送我们下去
What are you doing?
你要干什么
Oh, my.
噢 我的天哪
Behold Tai Lung.
看看 这就是大龙
I'm just gonna wait right here.
我...我还是待在这儿吧
It's nothing to worry about. It's perfectly safe.
没什么好担心的 万无一失
Orossbows! At the ready!
弩弓待命
Orossbows?
弩弓?
Hey, tough guy, did you hear?
嗨 牛人 你听说了吗?
Oogway's giving someone the Dragon Scroll, and it's not gonna be you.
乌龟要把神龙卷轴传人了 别想了 反正不会是你
Don't get him mad.
别把他惹恼了
What's he gonna do about it? I've got him completely immobilized.
他又能怎么着 我已经把他捆结实了
Did I step on the wittle kitty's tail?
喔 我是不是踩到小猫咪的尾巴了?
I'm good. I've seen enough.
够了 我看够了
I'll tell Shifu he has nothing to worry about.
我会跟师父说没啥可担心的
No, he doesn't.
当然不用担心
I'll tell him that.
我会告诉他的
Can we please go now?
咱们能走了吗?
Dragon Warrior! Dragon Warrior!
神龙大侠! 神龙大侠!
Wait a second!
等一下
I think there's been a slight mistake. Everyone seems to think that I'm...
我想这是个小误会 大家都以为我是...
The Sacred Hall of Warriors! No way!
奇侠圣殿! 不会吧!
Look at this place.
瞧瞧这地儿
Master Flying Rhino's armor with authentic battle damage!
飞天犀牛大师的盔甲 还有货真价实的战斗破损!
The Sword of Heroes!
英雄之刃!
Said to be so sharp you can cut yourself just by looking.
据说吹毛断发 看看都会受伤
The Invisible Trident of Destiny!
隐形的命运之杖!
I've only seen paintings of that painting.
我只见过这画的临摹版
No!
不会吧
The legendary Urn of Whispering Warriors.
传说中的英灵窃语之瓮
Said to contain the souls of the entire Tenshu Army.
据说里面有整个天书军团的灵魂
Hello.
你们好
Have you finished sight-seeing?
你观光完毕了吗?
Sorry, I should have come to you first.
对不起 我该先来看你
My patience is wearing thin.
我的耐心有限
Well, I mean, it's not like you were going anywhere.
不过 看起来你也没法去哪儿
- Would you turn around? - Sure.
- 你能转过身来吗? - 当然
How's it going?
嗨 这样怎么样
How do you get 5,000... Master Shifu!
你是怎么让五千... 师父大师
Someone... broke that.
有人把这个打碎了
But I'll fix it. Do you have some...
但我会把它黏好的 你有没有...
...glue?
...胶水?
A splinter.
啊，扎手了
So you're the legendary Dragon Warrior?
你就是那个传说中的"神龙大侠"?
- I guess so. - Wrong!
- 我想是吧 - 错!
You are not the Dragon Warrior. You will never be the Dragon Warrior until...
你不是也不可能是神龙大侠 除非
...you have learned the secret of the Dragon Scroll.
除非你掌握了神龙卷轴里的秘密
So, how does this work?
那我怎么上去呢
Do you have a ladder or a trampoline, or...?
你有梯子或者蹦床或者...
You think it's that easy? That I'll just hand you the secret
你想的太简单了 我会把那无限力量的秘密
- to limitless power? - No, I...
- 就这么交给你? - 不是的 我...
One must first master the highest level of kung fu.
一个人必须先达到功夫的最高境界
And that is impossible if that one is someone like you.
而像你这样的是不可能了
Someone like me?
像我这样?
Yes, look at you! This fat butt! Flabby arms!
没错 瞧瞧你 这肥臀 这肥胳膊
Those are sensitive in the flabby parts.
啊 这些赘肉可都娇贵的很呢
And this ridiculous belly.
还有这滑天下之大稽的大肚皮
And utter disregard for personal hygiene.
还有 一点儿也不讲卫生
Now, wait a minute. That's uncalled for.
慢着 这么说可有点过分了
Don't stand that close. I can smell your breath.
别站这么近 口臭都出来了
Listen, Oogway said I was...
听着 乌龟大师说我是...
The WuXi Finger Hold. Not the WuXi Finger Hold!
啊 巫师指 别用巫师指
Oh, you know this hold?
噢 你知道这个指法
Developed by Master WuXi in the Third Dynasty.
第三王朝时 巫师大师发明的
Then you know what happens when I fleX my pinky.
那你一定知道 一旦弯下小指会发生什么了
- No, no! - You know the hardest part of this?
- 别 千万别 - 你知道最难办的是什么吗?
The hardest part is cleaning up afterwards.
就是清理你的尸骨残骸
OK, OK, take it easy.
是的 没错 别激动
Now listen closely, panda.
那仔细听着 熊猫
Oogway may have picked you, but when I'm through with you,
乌龟大师也许选了你 可当我找上你
I promise you, you're going to wish he hadn't! Are we clear?
我向你保证 你会希望 他选的不是你! 清楚了吗?
Yeah, we're clear. We're so clear.
清楚了 一清二楚 十分清楚
Good.
很好 呵呵
I can't wait to get started.
我都等不及要开始了
- Let's begin. - Wait, wait, wait.
- 开始吧 - 等等
What?
什么?
- Now? - Yes, now.
- 现在吗? - 就现在!
Unless the great Oogway was wrong and you are not the Dragon Warrior.
除非你认为了不起的乌龟大师错了 而你也不是"神龙大侠"
Oh, OK, well...
好吧
I don't know if I can do all of those moves.
我不知道我能不能.. 把那些招式都比划出来
Well, if we don't try we'll never know, will we?
不试试 又怎么能知道呢
Yeah, it's just, maybe we can find something more suited to my level.
是啊 但能不能从更合适我这个级别的开始
What level is that?
那你的级别又是什么呢?
Well, I'm not a master, but...
你知道...我不是大师
...let's just start at zero. Level zero.
不如从零级开始 零级
No. There is no such thing as level zero.
不 从来没有零级的说法
- Maybe I can start with that. - That?
- 嘿 也许我可以从那开始 - 那个?
We use that for training children and propping the door open when it's hot.
我们用来训练孩子 天热的时候还用来顶门
But if you insist...
可要是你坚持的话...
The Furious Five!
喔 是"盖世五侠"!
You're bigger than your action figures. EXcept, you, Mantis. You're the same.
你们可比功夫公仔大多了 除了你 螳螂 你还是那么大
Go ahead, panda. Show us what you can do.
开始吧 熊猫 让我们看看你的能耐
Are they gonna watch, or should I wait till they get back to work?
你们就在这看我打? 还是我应该等你们都回去再开始...
Hit it.
出招
OK, yeah. I mean, I just ate. So I'm still digesting.
好吧 我刚吃完东西 还在消化
So my kung fu might not be as good as... later on.
所以我的功夫可能不像过一会儿那么好
Just hit it.
快出招!
All right.
好吧
What you got? You got nothing 'cause I got it right here.
你算老几啊? 有我在这儿你啥都不算
You picking on my friends? Get ready to feel thunder.
你找我朋友的茬? 准备受死吧
I'm coming at you with crazy feet. What you gonna do about crazy feet?
看我佛山无影脚 你没辙了吧?
Come on. I'm a blur. You've never seen bear style.
来啊 给你来个移形幻影 没见识过熊猫功夫吧
You've only seen praying mantis.
你就知道螳臂
Or monkey style.
猴拳
Or I could come at you snickety-snake.
我还会金蛇狂舞
Would you hit it!
你能出招吗?!
All right. All right.
好吧 好吧
Why don't you try again? A little harder.
再来一次 重点儿打
How's that?
怎样...啊
That hurts.
疼死我了!
This will be easier than I thought.
这比我想得可简单多了
I'm feeling a little nauseous!
我感到有点想吐!
Those are hard!
这么硬!
My tenders.
我的命根子
How did I do?
我表现如何
There is now a level zero.
算得上零级了
- There's no words. - No denying that.
- 简直无语 - 没错
What was Master Oogway thinking?
真不懂乌龟大师怎么想的
The poor guy's gonna get himself killed.
那可怜的孩子 差点把自己弄死
He is so mighty!
他太"无敌"了!
The Dragon Warrior fell out of the sky on a ball of fire!
"神龙大侠"坐在火球上从天而降!
When he walks, the very ground shakes!
举手投足 地动山摇!
One would think Master Oogway would choose someone who knew kung fu.
本以为乌龟大师会选一个会功夫的
Yeah, or could at least touch his toes.
没错 起码是一个能够到脚趾头的
Or even see his toes.
至少也要能看到自己的脚趾头吧
OK.
不错 都睡了
Great.
很好 就这样
Hi. You're up.
嗨 你醒啦
I am now.
这下是了
I was just...
我只是
Some day, huh?
不简单的一天哈
That kung fu stuff is hard work, right? Are your biceps sore?
功夫可够累人的哈 你肱二头肌酸不酸?
I've had a long and rather disappointing day, so...
今天已经是又长又失望的一天了 所以...
Yeah, I should probably get to sleep now.
我差不多也该睡觉了
- Yeah, yeah, yeah. Of course. - OK, thanks.
- 对对 当然 - 谢谢
It's just... Man, I'm such a big fan!
我只是... 我可是你们的超级粉丝哦
You guys were amazing at the Battle of Weeping River.
泣河一战 你们实在太牛了
Outnumbered a thousand to one but you didn't stop. You just...
你们以一挡千 你们毫无惧意 你们如同...
Sorry about that.
哦 不好意思
Look, you don't belong here.
听着 你不属于这儿
I know. I know. You're right.
呃 我知道 说的没错
I don't have... I just...
我没啥... 我只是...
My whole life I dreamed of...
我一生都梦想着...
No, I meant you don't belong here. I mean, in this room. This is my room.
不 我指你不属于"这儿" 我指这个房间 这是我的房间
Property of Orane.
仙鹤产权所有
OK. Right, right.
哦 确实 确实
So, you want to get to sleep.
那么...你想睡觉了
- Yeah. - I'm keeping you up.
- 是的 - 我妨碍你了
We got big things tomorrow.
明天还有要事呢
All right. You're awesome. Last thing I'm gonna say. Bye-bye.
好吧 你很彪悍! 我就说这么多 拜拜
What was that?
你刚说什么?
I didn't say anything.
我什么都没说
OK. All right. Good night.
好的 晚安
Sleep well.
好梦!
That seemed a little awkward.
貌似有点尴尬
Master Tigress! I didn't mean to wake you.
娇虎大师! 没想吵醒你
- You don't belong here. - Yeah, of course.
- 你不属于这里! - 是的 当然
This is your room.
这是你的房间
I mean, you don't belong in the Jade Palace.
我的意思是 你不配待在翡翠宫
You're a disgrace to kung fu,
你让功夫蒙羞
and if you have any respect for who we are and what we do,
如果你对我们 还有我们的事业存有敬重
you will be gone by morning.
明早前 你就该走人
Big fan!
超级粉丝哦
I see you have found the Sacred Peach Tree of Heavenly Wisdom.
看来你找到了圣智桃树啊
Is that what this is? Sorry. I thought it was just a regular peach tree.
这就是? 抱歉我以为它就是棵普通桃树
I understand. You eat when you are upset.
我能理解 你不开心的时候就会吃东西
Upset? I'm not upset. What makes you think I'm upset.
不开心? 我没不开心啊 什么让你认为我不开心了?
So why are you so upset?
那你为什么不开心呢?
I probably sucked more today than anyone in the history of kung fu.
我可能是功夫史上最烂的
In the history of China. In the history of sucking!
中国史上最烂的 烂人史上也是最烂的!
Probably.
可能
And the Five! Man, you should've seen them! They totally hate me.
看看"盖世五侠"! 你该看看 他们对我恨之入骨啊!
Totally.
不假
How is Shifu ever going to turn me into the Dragon Warrior?
师父怎么可能把我变成"神龙大侠"啊?
I mean, I'm not like the Five.
我一点也不像"五侠"
I've got no claws, no wings, no venom.
我没爪子 没翅膀 也没毒牙
Even Mantis has those... thingies.
就连螳螂 也有那些...镰刀
Maybe I should just quit and go back to making noodles.
唉 也许我就该一走了之 回家煮面
Quit, don't quit.
回家? 不回家?
Noodles, don't noodles.
煮面? 不煮面?
You are too concerned with what was and what will be.
你太在意过去曾怎样 将来会怎样
There's a saying:
有句谚语说得好
Yesterday is history,
昨天已是历史
tomorrow is a mystery,
明天还很神秘
but today is a gift.
但是今天是一个礼物
That is why it is called the present.
这就是为什么要把它叫做"当下"
- Oh, no! - What's happening?!
- 噢 不会吧 - 发生什么了?
To your battle stations! Go! Go! Go!
去你的战斗位置 快 快
Fire crossbows!
弩弓发射!
Fire!
发射!
Tai Lung is free! I must warn Shifu.
大龙越狱了! 我必须去警告师父
- Not going anywhere! Neither is he! - Let go of me!
- 你哪也去不了! 他也一样! - 放开我!
Bring it up!
把它拉起来
Wait! Bring it back!
等等 先放下来
- He's coming this way! - He won't get far. Archers!
- 他朝这来了 - 他过不来的 弓箭手
We're dead. So very, very dead.
我们死翘翘了 死得很翘很翘了!
Not yet we're not. Now!
还没呢 至少现在还没!
- Can we run now? - Yes.
- 现在能跑了么 - 能了
I'm glad Shifu sent you.
我很高兴师父派你来
I was beginning to think I'd been forgotten.
我还以为都把我忘了呢
Fly back there and tell them...
飞回去跟他们说
...the real Dragon Warrior is coming home.
真正的"神龙大侠" 要回家了
Good morning, Master!
早上好 大师
Panda!
熊猫!
Wake up!
起床!
He's quit.
他果然走了
What do we do now, with the panda gone? Who will be the Dragon Warrior?
我们现在做什么 熊猫走了 谁会成为"神龙大侠"呢?
All we can do is resume our training and trust that in time,
我们能做的 就是勤加练习 假以时日
the true Dragon Warrior will be revealed.
真正的"神龙大侠"便会脱颖而出
What are you doing here?!
你在这干吗?
Hi! Good morning, Master!
早上好 大师
I thought I'd warm up a little.
我想先热热身
You're stuck.
你卡住了
Stuck? Nah. What? Stuck?
卡住了? 什么 哪有?
Nah. This is one of my... Yeah, I'm stuck.
没有 我只是在... 好吧 我卡住了
- Help him. - Oh, dear.
- 去帮他 - 受不了
Maybe on three. One, two...
我数到三! 一 二
...three.
...三
- Thank you. - Don't mention it.
- 谢谢 - 别提这事
- No, really, I appreciate... - Ever.
- 不 我真的很感激... - 永远别提!
You actually thought you could learn to do a full split in one night?
你真以为你能一夜练成劈叉?
It takes years to develop one's flexibility!
这可是数年苦练 才习得的柔韧
And years longer to apply it in combat!
再加以数载 才能用于实战
Put that down!
把-那-放-下-来!
The only souvenirs we collect here are bloody knuckles and broken bones.
我们收集的纪念品 只会是残肢断臂
Yeah! EXcellent.
酷 棒极了!
Let's get started.
让我们开始吧
- Are you ready? - I was born re...
- 你准备好了吗? - 我打小就准备...啊!
I'm sorry, brother. I thought you said you were ready.
真不好意思 我以为你说的是你早已准备好了呢
That was awesome! Let's go again!
真是太酷了 再来
I've been taking it easy on you, panda. But no more.
我一直都对你手下留情 熊猫 但到此为止
Your next opponent will be me.
你下一个对手 就是我
All right! Yeah, let's go!
太棒了 来吧
Step forth.
上前一步
The true path to victory is to find your opponent's weakness...
取胜的两个诀窍就是 找到对手的软肋
...and make him suffer for it.
并让他痛不欲生
Oh, yeah!
爽
To take his strength and use it against him...
借力打力
...until he finally falls...
直到他倒地不起
...or quits.
或求饶认输
A real warrior never quits.
真的大侠绝不言弃
Don't worry, Master. I will never quit!
别担心 大师 我永远不会放弃的!
If he's smart he won't come back up those steps.
如果他够聪明 他不会再爬上来了
But he will.
可他会上来的
He's not going to quit, is he?
他不会放弃的 是吧?
He's not going to quit bouncing I'll tell you that.
我能告诉你的是 他不会放弃弹跳的
I thought you said acupuncture would make me feel better.
我记得你说针灸会让我好受些
Trust me, it will.
相信我 会的
It's just not easy finding the right nerve points under all this...
只是不容易找准你的穴位 都是些...
- Fat? - Fur. I was going to say fur.
- 脂肪? - 毛皮 我是想说毛皮的
Sure you were.
才怪
Who am I to judge a warrior based on his size? Look at me.
我怎么会用体型来评价一个大侠 看看我
I'm over here.
我在这里
Maybe you should look at this again.
也许你得再看看这个
Oh, OK.
噢 好吧
Stop it. Stop!
住手 住手...啊!
I know Master Shifu is trying to inspire me and all...
我知道师父大师是在激励我
...but if I didn't know better I'd say he was trying to get rid of me.
要不是我了解他 我还以为他是想撵我走
I know he can seem kind of heartless...
我知道他看上去有点无情
...but he wasn't always like that.
可他原本不是这样的
According to legend
传说
there was once a time when Master Shifu actually used to smile.
很久以前 师父也曾笑口常开
- No! - Yes.
- 不可能 - 真的
But that was before.
那是在...之前
Before what?
在什么之前?
Before Tai Lung.
在大龙之前
We're not really supposed to talk about him.
我们不该提起他的
Well, if he's going to stay here he should know.
要是他打算留下 就该知道
Guys, guys, I know about Tai Lung.
各位 各位 我知道大龙
He was a student. The first ever to master the thousand scrolls of kung fu.
他是有史以来第一个 学会了师父千般武艺的徒弟
And then he turned bad and now he's in jail.
然后他变坏了 再然后...就蹲大牢了...
He wasn'tjust a student.
他不只是个徒弟
Shifu found him as a cub...
师父捡到他时 他还在襁褓之中
...and he raised him as his son.
师父抚养他长大 视同己出
And when the boy showed talent in kung fu...
当发现那小子天生就是武学奇才时
...Shifu trained him.
师父倾其所能悉心教导
He believed in him. He told him he was destined for greatness.
信任他 跟他说必成大器
It was never enough for Tai Lung.
大龙他永远不满足
He wanted the Dragon Scroll.
他想得到神龙卷轴
But Oogway saw darkness in his heart and refused.
可乌龟大师洞察到了他心中的黑暗 拒绝传给他
Outraged, Tai Lung laid waste to the valley.
盛怒之下 大龙血洗山谷
He tried to take the scroll by force.
他试图强行夺取卷轴
And Shifu had to destroy what he had created.
师父不得不斩除自己种下的祸根
But how could he?
可他怎么忍心呢?
Shifu loved Tai Lung like he had never loved anyone before.
师父之前从没像爱大龙那样爱过别人
Or since.
或许 从那之后也没有
And now he has a chance to make things right.
而现在他有机会 来拨乱返正
To train the true Dragon Warrior.
训练真正的"神龙大侠"
And he's stuck with you.
却碰到了你
A big fat panda who treats it like a joke.
这只又肥又胖视练武如儿戏的熊猫
That is it!
够了!
Wait! My fault! I accidentally tweaked his facial nerve.
等等 我的错! 我不小心扎到了他的面部穴位
And may have also stopped his heart.
好像心脏也被扎停了
Inner peace.
平心静气
Inner...
平心...
Inner peace.
平心静气
Would whoever is making that flapping sound quiet down?!
谁在呼扇呼扇的? 给我安静!
Inner...
平心...
Oh, Zeng.
噢 小曾
Excellent.
太好了
I could use some good news right now.
我现在正需要一些好消息
Master! Master!
大师 大师
I have... It's... It's very bad news.
我有一个... 一个... 很坏的消息
Shifu.
师父
There is just news. There is no good or bad.
消息就是消息 没有好坏之分
Master, your vision. Your vision was right.
大师 你的幻相...你的幻相应验了!
Tai Lung has broken out of prison. He's on his way.
大龙越狱了 他正在赶来!
That is bad news...
这还真是坏消息
...if you do not believe that the Dragon Warrior can stop him.
如果你不相信"神龙大侠"可以阻止他的话
The panda? Master that panda is not the Dragon Warrior.
那只熊猫? 大师 那熊猫可不是什么"神龙大侠"
He wasn't meant to be here! It was an accident.
他根本不该在这儿 那只是个巧合
There are no accidents.
没有巧合
Yes, I know. You've said that already.
是的我知道 你已经说过...
- Twice. - Well, that was no accident, either.
- 两遍了 - 这也不是偶然.
Thrice.
三遍了
My old friend,
我的老朋友
the panda will never fulfill his destiny, nor you yours,
阿宝没法完成他的使命 你也一样
until you let go of the illusion of control.
除非假象不再蒙蔽你的眼睛
Illusion?
假象
Yes. Look at this tree, Shifu.
没错 看看这棵树 师父
I cannot make it blossom when it suits me,
我无法强迫它随时开花
nor make it bear fruit before its time.
也不能令它提前结果
But there are things we can control.
但是 有些事情我们可以控制
I can control when the fruit will fall.
我可以左右果子何时落地
And I can control...
我还可以左右种子...
...where to plant the seed.
种于何地
That is no illusion, Master.
这可不是假象 大师
Yes.
没错
But no matter what you do,
即便如此 无论你做什么
that seed will grow to be a peach tree.
这种子终会长成桃树
You may wish for an apple or an orange but you will get a peach.
你也许想要苹果或是橘子 但你能得到的只能是桃子
But a peach cannot defeat Tai Lung!
但是桃子不能打败大龙
Maybe it can.
也许可以呢
If you are willing to guide it.
只要你愿意对其谆谆教导
To nurture it.
悉心培养
To believe in it.
心存信念
But how? How?
但是 得怎么做呢? 要怎么做呢?
I need your help, Master.
我需要你的帮助 大师
No, you just need to believe.
不需要 你只需要相信
Promise me, Shifu.
答应我 师父
Promise me you will believe.
答应我你会相信
I will try.
我...尽量
Good.
很好
My time has come.
我的时辰到了
You must continue yourjourney without me.
你得孤身前行了
What are you...? Wait!
什... 什...你说什么...等等
Master!
大师!
You can't leave me!
不要丢下我一个
You must believe.
你必须相信
Master!
大师!
Scary? Yeah, so I'm like "Fine, you may be a wolf,
吓人吧? 我说 就算你是豺狼...
you may be the scariest bandit in Haijin Province...
或是福建第一恶霸
...but you're a lousy tipper."
可你给小费太小气啦
Really? So how did you get out of there alive?
真的? 那你是怎么活着回来的?
I mean, I didn't actually say that...
我是说... 我没有真的说出口
...but I thought it...
我只是心里
...in my mind.
这么想
If he could read my mind he'd be, like, "What?"
他要是会读心术的话 一定会说:"大胆!"
Order up! Hope you like it.
面来咯 希望你们会喜欢
- This is really good! - No, come on.
- 味道好极了 - 得了吧
Try my dad's Secret Ingredient Soup. He actually knows the secret ingredient.
你得尝尝我老爸的私酿密汤 只有他知道秘方
What do you mean? This is amazing!
说什么呢 这味道棒极了
- You're a really good cook. - I wish my mouth was bigger.
- 你可真会煮 - 真希望嘴巴大一点
Tigress, you've got to try this.
娇虎 快尝尝
It is said that the Dragon Warrior can survive for months
相传"神龙大侠"单靠银杏甘露
on nothing but the dew of ginkgo leaf and the energy of the universe.
和日月精华 就能活好几个月
I guess my body doesn't know it's the Dragon Warrior yet.
我猜我的身体还没意识到它成了"神龙大侠"呢
I'm gonna need a lot more than dew and universe juice.
光靠甘露和精华可没法活
- What? - Nothing... Master Shifu.
- 笑啥? - 没啥 师父大师
Never be the Dragon Warrior unless you lose 500 pounds and brush your teeth!
你永远都成不了"神龙大侠" 除非你减500磅膘 刷干净牙
What is that noise you're making? Laughter? I never heard of it!
吵什么吵?! 笑声 我听都没听过
Work hard, panda, and maybe someday...
努力吧 熊猫 也许有一天
...you will have ears like mine.
你可以拥有像我一样的耳朵
That's good.
还真像
Ears. It's not working for you? I thought they were pretty good.
耳朵 不好笑吗? 我觉得挺逗的
It's Shifu!
是师父!
Of course it's Shifu. What do you think I'm doing?
当然是师父 不然你以为我在模仿谁?
Master Shifu!
噢... 师父大师
You think this is funny?
你们觉得好笑吗?
Tai Lung has escaped and you're acting like children!
大龙越狱了 你们还跟个小孩子一样!
- What? - He is coming for the Dragon Scroll,
- 什么? - 他是冲着"神龙卷轴"来的
and you are the only one who can stop him.
而你是唯一可以阻止他的人
And I was saying you got no sense of humor.
哈哈 我说的没错吧 你还真不懂幽默
I'm gonna... stop Tai Lung.
要我...阻止大龙
What? You're serious? And I have to...?
啥?! 你当真? 真要我去?
Master Oogway will stop him like he did before, he'll do it again.
乌龟大师会阻止他的 就像他上次那样
Oogway cannot!
乌龟不能
Not anymore.
再也不能了
Our only hope is the Dragon Warrior.
我们唯一的希望就只剩下"神龙大侠"了
- The panda? - Yes, the panda!
- 靠这熊猫? - 就靠这熊猫
Master, please, let us stop Tai Lung. This is what you've trained us for.
师父 拜托 让我们来阻止大龙 这也是你教我们武功的目的
No! It is not your destiny to defeat Tai Lung.
不 打败大龙不是你的使命
It is his!
而是他的!
Where'd he go?
人呢?
You cannot leave! A real warrior never quits.
你不可以走 真的大侠是永不言弃的
Watch me.
看看我
Come on.
拜托
How am I supposed to beat Tai Lung? I can't even beat you to the stairs.
我凭什么打败大龙 我连绕过你下山都做不到
You will beat him because you are the Dragon Warrior.
你可以打败他 因为你是"神龙大侠"
You don't believe that. You never believed that.
你不信这鬼话 你从没信过这鬼话
From the beginning you've tried to get rid of me.
我初来乍到的时候 你不是想方设法把我踹走?
Yes! I was.
没错 那是以前
But now I ask you to trust in your master as I have come to trust in mine.
但现在 我要你相信你的师父 就像我相信我的师父那样
You're not my master. And I'm not the Dragon Warrior.
你不是我师父 我也不是什么"神龙大侠"
Then why didn't you quit?! You knew I wanted you gone, yet you stayed.
那你为什么不放弃 你明知道我要赶你走 但你还是留下了
Yeah, I stayed.
没错 我是留下了
I stayed because every time you threw a brick at my head,
我留下是因为 每次你往我头上拍砖
or said I smelled, it hurt but it could never hurt more,
或者说我难闻 是会让我伤心 但这些都赶不上以前
than it did every day of my life just being me.
过去天天浑浑噩噩 更让我伤心
I stayed because I thought if anyone could change me...
我留下 是因为我知道 要是还有人能改变我
...could make me... not me...
可以让我超越自己
...it was you.
那个人就是你
The greatest kung fu teacher in all of China!
全中国最了不起的功夫师父
But I can change you!
我可以改变你!
I can turn you into the Dragon Warrior! And I will!
我可以让你成为"神龙大侠" 我会做到的!
Come on. Tai Lung is on his way here right now.
拜托 大龙马上就要赶到了
Even if it takes him a hundred years to get here, how are you...
就算他要在路上耗上一百年
...gonna change this into the Dragon Warrior?
你又怎么能把眼前这个肥仔训练成神龙大侠?
How?
有办法吗?
有吗?
- How?! - I don't know!
- 没有了吧? - 我不知道
I don't know.
我不知道
That's what I thought.
我就知道
This is what you trained me for.
养兵千日 用兵一时
Tigress!
娇虎!
Don't try and stop me.
别想拦我!
We're not trying to stop you.
我们不是要拦你
What?
什么?
We're coming with you!
我们是要跟你并肩作战
What? I eat when I'm upset, OK?
怎么啦? 我不开心就吃 不行吗?
No need to explain.
噢 不必解释
I thought you might be Monkey. He hides his almond cookies on the top shelf.
我还以为是金猴呢 他总把杏仁饼干藏在架子最上面
Don't tell Monkey.
别跟猴哥说
- Look at you. - Yeah, I know, I disgust you.
- 看看你 - 我知道 我让你看了恶心
No, I mean, how did you get up there?
不 我是说 你是怎么爬上去的?
I don't know. I guess that...
不晓得 我只是...
I don't know. I was getting a cookie.
不晓得 我只是想着饼干
Yet you are ten feet off the ground.
然后你就瞬间离地十尺
And you have done a perfect spilt.
而且还做出了完美的劈叉
No, this? This is just...
不是啦 这只是...
...an accident.
误打误撞
There are no accidents.
根本就没有什么误打误撞
Come with me.
跟我来
I know you're trying to be all mystical and kung fuey...
我知道你为教我武功 故弄玄虚
...but could you at least tell me where we're going?
但也至少告诉我现在是去哪吧?
You dragged me...
你...
...all the way out here...
让我累死累活爬上来...
...for a bath?
就为了让我洗白白?
Panda...
熊猫
...we do not wash our pits in the Pool of Sacred Tears.
这池神圣之泪可不是给你洗胳肢窝的
The Pool of...
这池是...
This is where Oogway unraveled the mysteries...
这是乌龟大师参透禅机的地方
...of harmony and focus.
两极调和 心无旁骛
This is the birthplace...
这就是功夫的
...of kung fu.
发源地
Do you want to learn kung fu?
你想学功夫吗?
Yeah!
当然
Then I am your master!
那么我就是你的师父
OK!
明白
Don't cry.
不要哭
OK.
好的
When you focus on kung fu,
当你一心想着功夫
when you concentrate...
想要心无杂念
...you stink.
你就会搞臭
Perhaps that is my fault.
不过那也许是我的错
I cannot train you the way I have trained the Five.
我不该一成不变 像教导"五侠"一样教导你
I now see that the way to get through to you...
现在我明白了 要你学好武功
...is with this.
就得靠这个
Oh, great, 'cause I am hungry.
噢 太棒了 我快饿扁了
Good.
很好
When you have been trained, you may eat.
等你练完 就能吃了
Let us begin.
开始吧
After you, panda.
你先请
Just like that?
这么简单?
No sit-ups? No ten-mile hike?
不需要仰卧起坐? 不需要十里长跑?
I vowed to train you, and you have been trained. You are free to eat.
我起誓教你武功 你也学有所成 你可以尽情享用了
Enjoy.
多吃点
Hey!
嘿
I said you are free to eat. Have a dumpling.
我说了你可以尽情享用 来个饺子
Hey!
你干嘛
You are free to eat.
尽情享用
- Am I?! - Are you?!
- 可以吗!? - 你说呢?!
I'm not hungry.
我不饿
Master.
师父
Cut it!
砍断吊桥!
Where's the Dragon Warrior?
"神龙大侠"怎么没来?
How do you know you're not looking at her?
你怎么知道我不是?
You think I'm a fool?
你当我傻?
I know you're not the Dragon Warrior. None of you!
我知道你根本就不是神龙大侠 你们五个都不是
I heard how he fell out of the sky in a ball of fire.
我听说了 他坐着火球从天而降
That he's a warrior unlike anything the world has ever seen.
他才是大侠 前无古人
- Po? - So that is his name. Po.
- 阿宝? - 那就是他的名字? 阿宝
Finally, a worthy opponent.
我终于棋逢对手
Our battle will be legendary!
这场对决将流传万世
We've got this. Help her.
我们来拉住 你去帮她
Monkey!
金猴!
Go!
快去
What was I thinking?!
想啥呢
Mantis!
螳螂!
Now!
快上!
Shifu taught you well.
师父把你们教得不错
But he didn't teach you everything.
不过并没倾囊相授
You have done well, panda.
你表现不错 熊猫
Done well? Done well?
表现不错? 只是表现不错?
I've done awesome!
我表现彪悍!
The mark of a true hero is humility.
真英雄无不谦逊有加
But, yes, you have done...
话虽这样说 你表现确实...
...awesome.
彪悍
Guys? Guys?! They're dead!
伙计们? 是他们! 他们死了!
No, they're breathing. They're asleep? No, their eyes are open.
不对 还有气 睡着了? 眼睛睁着呢
We were no match for his nerve attach.
我们根本不是对手 都被点穴了
He's gotten stronger.
他越来越强了
Who? Tai Lung? Stronger?
谁? 大龙吗? 更强了?
He's too fast!
他太快了
Sorry, Po.
不好意思 阿宝
I thought we could stop him.
我以为我们能够阻止他的
He could have killed you.
他本来可以杀了你们的
Why didn't he?
那他为什么没呢?
So you could come back and strike fear into our hearts. But it won't work.
让你们活着回来引发恐惧 但这招不会得逞的
It might. I mean, a little.
这招可能有用... 有点用...
I'm pretty scared.
好吧 我真被吓到了
You can defeat him, panda!
你可以打败他的 熊猫
Are you kidding? If they can't?!
你在说笑吧? 连他们都不行
They're five masters. I'm just one me.
他们可是盖世"五"侠 我只是"一个"我而已
But you will have the one thing that no one else does.
但是 你拥有一样任何人都没有的东西
You really believe I'm ready?
你真的相信我已经准备好了?
You are...
是的
...Po.
阿宝
Behold the Dragon Scroll.
修习神龙卷轴吧
It is yours.
现在它是你的了
Wait. What happens when I read it?
等等 如果我读了它的话会怎么样
Legend says you will be able to hear a butterfly's wing beat.
没人知道 但据传说 你能听到蝴蝶振翅之声
Really? That's cool.
真的? 酷!
Yes. And see light in the deepest cave.
是的 能在至暗之洞中明察秋毫
You will feel the universe in motion around you.
能感应周身天地的一举一动
Can I punch through walls?
哇哦! 我能打穿墙吗?
- Do a quadruple back flip? - Focus.
- 我能连做四个后空翻吗? - 心无杂念
- Will I...? - Focus.
- 我能...? - 心无杂念
- Focus. - Oh, yeah, yeah.
- 心无杂念 - 哦 好的 好的
Read it, Po, and fulfill your destiny.
阿宝 读吧 完成你的使命
Read it and become...
读吧 成为...
...the Dragon Warrior.
"神龙大侠"!
It's impossible to open.
根本打不开
OK. Come on, baby. Come on now.
别那么紧，快开开吧
Thank you.
谢谢
I probably loosened it up for you though.
也许是我刚才已经弄松了
OK, here goes.
好了 我要看了
- It's blank. - What?!
- 怎么是空白 - 啥?
- Here, look. - No, I am forbidden to look upon...
- 不信 你看 - 禁止旁人看的
Blank. I don't...
还真是空白 我...
I don't understand.
我想不通
OK. So, like...
好吧 就是说
...Oogway was just a crazy old turtle after all.
乌龟也不过就是只疯癫老龟
No. Oogway was wiser than us all.
不 乌龟大师的智慧无人能及
Oh, come on! Face it he picked me by accident.
拜托 面对现实吧 他只不过是碰巧选上了我
Of course I'm not the Dragon Warrior. Who am I kidding?
我当然不是什么"神龙大侠" 开什么玩笑
But who will stop Tai Lung?
可谁来阻止大龙呢?
He'll destroy everything and everyone.
他会毁了一切 并杀了每个人的
No.
不会的
Evacuate the valley. You must protect the villagers from Tai Lung's rage.
疏散整个山谷 你们必须保护村民们免受大龙的残暴
- What about you, Master? - I will fight him.
- 那您怎么办呢 师父? - 我来迎战他
- What? - I can hold him off long enough
- 什么? - 我能拖多久就拖多久
for everyone to escape.
这样大家都能全身而退
But, Shifu, he'll kill you.
但是 师父 他会杀了你的
Then I will finally have paid for my mistake.
那就算我为过错付出的代价吧
Listen to me, all of you.
都听我说
It is time for you to continue yourjourney without me.
没有我 你们也要继续走下去
I am very proud to have been your master.
身为你们的师父 我十分自豪
We've got to get them out safely.
我们必须让他们平安转移
Come, little one. Let's find your mama.
来 小家伙 我们去找妈妈
Viper, gather the southern farmers. Mantis, the north.
灵蛇 集合村子南边的人 螳螂 你去村北
Orane, light the way.
仙鹤 掌灯引路
Look, it's the Dragon Warrior.
看 那就是"神龙大侠"
Hey, Dad.
嗨 老爸
Po!
阿宝!
Good to have you back, son.
回来就好 儿子
Good to be back.
回来...就好...
Let's go, Po.
我们走吧 阿宝
So for our next shop it's time to face it...
看来 我们该规划下一家面馆了
...the future of noodles is dice-cut vegetables...
今后做面 菜要切成丁
...no longer slices.
不再切成丝了
Also, I was thinking, maybe this time
我还在想 趁着这次
we'll have a kitchen you can actually stand up in.
我们弄个大厨房 你就不用猫着腰了
You like that?
怎么样?
Po, I'm sorry if things didn't work out.
阿宝 我很遗憾 事不如愿
It just wasn't meant to be.
也许你就没那个命
Po, forget everything else.
阿宝 忘了这些不快吧
Your destiny still awaits.
你真正的命运还在等你呢
We are noodle folk. Broth runs deep through our veins.
我们是面条世家 血管里流淌着面汤
I don't know, Dad.
我不知道 老爸
Honestly, sometimes I can't believe I'm actually your son.
说实话 有时我甚至不相信我是你儿子
Po...
阿宝
...I think it's time I told you something I should have told you...
我想是时候告诉你 一些很久以前
...a long time ago.
就该告诉你的事了
OK.
好的
The secret ingredient of my Secret Ingredient Soup.
我那秘之又秘私酿密汤的配方...
Come here. The secret ingredient is...
...靠近点...秘之又秘的配方就是...
...nothing.
啥都没
You heard me. Nothing!
听到了么 啥都没!
There is no secret ingredient!
根本就没什么秘之又秘的配方!
Wait, wait. It's just plain old noodle soup?
等等 一切只不过是普通的面汤?
You don't add some kind of special sauce or something?
没加什么秘方酱汁 或者其他什么特别的东西?
Don't have to. To make something special, you just believe it's special.
没那必要 想让一件东西特别 你只要相信那是特别的就够了
There is no secret ingredient.
根本没有秘方
I have come home, Master.
我回家来了 师父
This is no longer your home. And I am no longer your master.
这里不再是你家 我也不再是你师父
Oh, yes. You have a new favorite.
是啊 你已经另有新宠了
So where is this Po?
那么 阿宝人呢?
Did I scare him off?
我把他吓跑了吗?
This battle is between you and me.
这是你我之间的战斗
So, that is how it's going to be.
那么 就如你所言吧
That is how it must be.
必须如我所言
I rotted in jail for 20 years because of your weakness!
我在大牢里蹲了20年 就因为你的懦弱!
Obeying your master is not weakness!
尊从师命 怎叫软弱
You knew I was the Dragon Warrior.
你原本知道的 我才是"神龙大侠"
You always knew.
你一直都知道
But when Oogway said otherwise what did you do?
但是当乌龟说"非也" 你做了什么?
What did you do?!
你做什么了?
Nothing!
什么都没做!
You were not meant to be the Dragon Warrior! That was not my fault!
你命中注定不是神龙大侠 那不是我的错!
Not your fault?!
不是你的错?
Who filled my head with dreams?!
是谁让我满怀梦想?
Who drove me to train until my bones cracked?!
是谁逼我练功练到骨错筋伤?
Who denied me my destiny?!
又是谁害我当不成神龙大侠?
It was never my decision to make!
那件事并非我能决定
It is now.
现在 你能了
Give me the scroll!
给-我-卷-轴!
I would rather die.
我宁可死
All I ever did, I did to make you proud!
我做的一切都是为了让你骄傲
Tell me how proud you are, Shifu!
告诉我你有多骄傲 师父!
Tell me!
你说啊!
你说!
I have... I have always been proud of you.
我...我一直都为你骄傲
From the first moment, I've been...
从一开始 我就
...proud of you.
为你骄傲
And it was my pride...
正是这种骄傲
...that blinded me.
蒙蔽了我双眼
I loved you too much to see what you were becoming...
对你的溺爱 让我看不到你的变化
...what I...
是因为我
...was turning you into.
你才变成这样的
I'm...
我...
I'm sorry.
我很抱歉
I don't want your apology.
我不要你的道歉
I want my scroll!
我要卷轴!
What?!
什么!
Where is it?!
卷轴去哪了?!
Dragon Warrior has taken the scroll halfway across China by now.
神龙大侠早已带着神龙卷轴远走高飞了
You will never see that scroll, Tai Lung.
你永远见不到那卷轴了 大龙
Never.
永远
Stairs.
台阶太多了...
Who are you?
你是谁?
Buddy, I am the Dragon Warrior.
伙计 我就是"神龙大侠"
You?
你?
Him? He's a panda.
他? 一只熊猫?
You're a panda. What are you gonna do, big guy? Sit on me?
你就是只熊猫 你想怎么着,大家伙? 一屁股坐死我?
Don't tempt me.
别把我惹毛了
Now. I'm gonna use this.
现在 我可要用这个了
You want it? Come and get it.
想要吗? 来拿啊!
Finally!
终于到手
That scroll is mine!
那个卷轴是我的!
Lightning!
快如闪电
The scroll has given him power!
卷轴给了他力量!
No!
不!
Finally! Oh, yes.
终于到手了 哦 太好了
The power of the Dragon Scroll is mine!
神龙卷轴的力量 是我的!
It's nothing!
怎么是空的?!
It's OK. I didn't get it the first time, either.
没关系 我第一次也没看出个所以然来
What?
什么?
There is no secret ingredient.
根本没有秘方
It's just you.
关键就在自己
Stop it!
停下
I'm gonna pee.
我都想尿尿了
Don't.
别戳
Don't! Don't!
别... 别戳了
You...
你...
...can't defeat me.
不可能打败我
You...
你...
...you're just a big...
你不过是只又肥...
...fat...
...又胖的...
...panda!
熊猫!
I'm not a big fat panda.
我不是什么又肥又胖的熊猫
I'm the big fat panda.
我是独一无二的又肥又胖的熊猫
The WuXi Finger Hold!
巫师指?!
Oh, you know this hold?
噢 你知道这招啊
You're bluffing. You're bluffing. Shifu didn't teach you that.
你唬我 你在唬我 师父不会教你的
Nope.
当然
I figured it out. Skadoosh.
我无师自通
Look!
看啊!
The Dragon Warrior.
是"神龙大侠"
That's my boy! That big lovely kung fu warrior is my son!
那个可爱的大块头功夫大侠 就是我儿子!
Yes!
儿子
Thanks, Dad.
谢谢你 老爸
Hey, guys.
嗨 伙计们
Master.
大师
Master?
Master Shifu!
师父大师
Master!
大师
Shifu, are you OK?!
师父 你还好吗?
Po.
阿宝
You're alive.
你还活着?
Or we're both dead.
还是咱俩都死了?
No, Master, I didn't die. I defeated Tai Lung.
不 师父 我没死 我打败了大龙
You did?
真的?
Wow. It is as Oogway foretold.
哇噢 正如乌龟所说
You are the Dragon Warrior.
你就是"神龙大侠"
You have brought peace...
你把平和
...to this valley...
带给这个山谷
...and...
也...
...and to me.
也带给了我
Thank you.
谢谢
Thank you, Po.
谢谢你 阿宝
Thank you. Thank you.
谢谢... 谢谢...
No! Master! No, no, no don't die, Shifu, please!
不不不 师父 别死啊!!
I'm not dying, you idiot!
我没死 你个白痴!
Ah. Dragon Warrior...
哦 "神龙大侠"
...I am simply at peace. Finally.
我只是在享受平和 终于平和了
So, I should stop talking?
噢 那我应该闭嘴?
If you can.
最好是
Want to get something to eat?
要不要...吃点啥?
Yeah.
好
∮ Everybody is kung fu fighting ∮
∮ 人人都爱比试武艺 ∮
∮ Your mind becomes fast as lightning ∮
∮ 你的思想闪电难及 ∮
∮ Although the future is a little bit frightening ∮
∮ 尽管前路有些恐惧 ∮
∮ It's the book of your life that you're writing ∮
∮ 你仍书写你的传奇 ∮
∮ Everybody is kung fu fighting ∮
∮ 人人都爱比试武艺 ∮
∮ Your mind becomes fast as lightning ∮
∮ 你的思想闪电难及 ∮
∮ Although the future is a little bit frightening ∮
∮ 尽管前路有些恐惧 ∮
∮ It's the book of your life that you're writing ∮
∮ 你仍书写你的传奇 ∮
∮ You are a natural ∮
∮ 你有如此高的天赋 ∮
∮ Why is that so hard to see? ∮
∮ 但又为何不为人知 ∮
∮ Maybe it's just because You keep on looking at me ∮
∮ 或许太过在乎自己 ∮
∮ The journey's a lonely one So much more than we know ∮
∮ 孤身之路远超想像 ∮
∮ But sometimes you've got to go And be your own hero ∮
∮ 但你必须英勇前往 ∮
∮ Everybody is kung fu fighting ∮
∮ 人人都爱比试武艺 ∮
∮ Your mind becomes fast as lightning ∮
∮ 你的思想闪电难及 ∮
∮ Although the future is a little bit frightening ∮
∮ 尽管前路有些恐惧 ∮
∮ It's the book of your life that you're writing ∮
∮ 你仍书写你的传奇 ∮
∮ You're a diamond in the rough A brilliant ball of clay ∮
∮ 你是沙粒中的钻石 ∮
∮ You could be a work of art If you just go all the way ∮
∮ 努力下去必将成器 ∮
∮ Now what would it take to break? I believe that you can bend ∮
∮ 只要你能坚持下去 ∮
∮ Not only do you have to fight But you have got to win ∮
∮ 战斗你一定能胜利 ∮
∮ 'Oause everybody is kung fu fighting ∮
∮ 人人都爱比试武艺 ∮
∮ Your mind becomes fast as lightning ∮
∮ 你的思想闪电难及 ∮
∮ Although the future is a little bit frightening ∮
∮ 尽管前路有些恐惧 ∮
∮ It's the book of your life that you're writing ∮
∮ 你仍书写你的传奇 ∮
∮ You're a diamond in the rough A brilliant ball of clay ∮
∮ 你是沙粒中的钻石 ∮
∮ You could be a work of art If you just go all the way ∮
∮ 努力下去必将成器 ∮
∮ Now what would it take to break? I believe that you can bend ∮
∮ 只要你能坚持下去 ∮
∮ Not only do you have to fight But you have got to win ∮
∮ 战斗你一定能胜利 ∮
∮ 'Oause everybody is kung fu fighting ∮
∮ 人人都爱比试武艺 ∮
∮ Your mind becomes fast as lightning ∮
∮ 你的思想闪电难及 ∮
∮ Although the future is a little bit frightening ∮
∮ 尽管前路有些恐惧 ∮
∮ It's the book of your life that you're writing ∮
∮ 你仍书写你的传奇 ∮